one of the most frequent questions that
people ask me from time to time is the
question what is existentialism
and my standard reply to the question is
existentialism is the philosophy of
existence
and when I give that kind of an answer
to people kind of look at me like to say
thank you very much that doesn't really
help
well we'll be looking in the lectures to
come at some of the most important
characteristics of modern existential
philosophy because apart from Marxism
there's been no philosophy that has such
a radical impact on our own culture as
this philosophy has had in the last 50
years or so
now the philosophy called existentialism
has its roots in the 19th century in two
distinct varieties or kinds of
existential philosophy there is on the
one hand that existential philosophy
that is called
pessimistic existentialism or atheistic
existentialism which is distinguished
from an existential movement that sought
a synthesis with historic Christianity
and the most important figure for
Christian existentialism in the 19th
century and many regard as the father of
modern existential thought at least as
it impacts theology is the Danish
philosopher Soren Kierkegaard and we'll
look at him separately but today I want
to look at the 19th century father of
atheistic existentialism whose name is
Frederick Nietzsche now everybody's
heard of Nietzsche he's famous for the
saying that God is dead Nietzsche was
born towards the middle of the 19th
century in 1844 and he died at the turn
of the century in 1900 the last 11 years
of his life were spent in insanity and
he had been committed to a lunatic
asylum for those final periods of his
life
but Nietzsche was a student of history
and a student of 19th century culture
and he began with a complaint against
the chief characteristics of 19th
century European culture which he
described as being decadent
and to be decadent means to be in a
process of radical Decay or corruption
now Nietzsche saw this decadence as
being driven by the negative influence
of the Christian church because the
Christian Church
posited certain values that Nietzsche
was convinced would undermine and
destroy the human spirit for example the
ethic of Christianity stresses grace and
mercy and pity
and for Nietzsche these so-called
Christian virtues in still weakness into
people and cause them to live in an
unthinking and non-creative way a way
that sort of uh
dwarfs the basic human spirit and
destroys what the existentialists call
authentic human existence
and Nietzsche saw that the necessary
antidote for the survival of Western
civilization and for culture to reach
its potential
that first of all what had to happen was
we had to get rid of this
sentimental religion that blinded people
from the reality of human existence as
we find it Nietzsche is often considered
the modern father of nihilism
and nihilism
basically has the Creed that there are
no Eternal truths there is no Eternal
purpose and there is no ultimate meaning
or significance to human existence
that in the final analysis what we meet
in life is what Nietzsche called the
nothingness the nothingness of
meaninglessness there is no God and
because there is no God there is no
ultimate meaning to human life and
that's what is meant by nihilism or the
nothingness of Human Experience
now his thought was formed in his
college days and he advocated an
approach to existence called biological
heroism
biological heroism which was articulated
in part in his most famous work in
German also sprock zarathustra or in
English Thus Spoke zarathustra who was
the prophet of the age who declared the
death of God now in this declaration of
the death of God nature described how
this took place in two stages
he said somewhat tongue-in-cheek that
originally there was a Pantheon full of
gods and goddesses and Western
Civilization had a view of polytheism
where he had a God for this and a God
for that and he said that what caused
the death of all of the rest of the Gods
and ushered in monotheism was when this
Jewish god stood up in the midst of the
Assembly of all of the deities and
declared to the universe Thou shalt have
no other gods besides me
and he said when this Jewish deity made
that outrageous claim of exclusivity
that the rest of the Gods broke out
laughing and they laughed so hard they
laughed themselves to death and so only
one God was left the god Yahweh and of
course this God then later succumbed and
his fatal illness that is that which
killed God According to Nietzsche was
pity
God is dead he died of pity he died from
this same weakness that has now been
infected in Western culture and the
response to this is to create a new
existential Humanity
based on what he called biological
heroism now by the way in passing
it's important to know that as a
historical footnote that during his
struggles in his early years before he
came to the full level of power that he
enjoyed the Bavarian Corporal Adolf
Hitler sent copies of Nietzsche's Works
to all of his close friends and henchmen
because he was convinced that he found
in Nietzsche the justification for
creating a new super order or super race
of people the Aryan race that he sought
to Institute Scholars disagree as to
whether Hitler was taking Nietzsche to
his logical conclusion or was simply
distorting Nietzsche in the process but
in any case he does have this view of
biological heroism whereby we need a new
kind of authentic existence which
existence will be modeled by what he
called the ubermench or in Translation
is the phrase
Superman
and as the word super or the German Uber
suggests is that this new model of
humanity the Superman will be higher
above and beyond the normal course of
humanity now to understand that we have
to understand something of Nietzsche's
basic anthropology
we've seen that
historically we've defined human beings
in terms of homo sapiens we saw how that
was challenged by Mark substitution of
the phrase homo Faber because it's our
labor the chiefly characterizes and
distinguishes our uniqueness as people
Nietzsche on the other hand was
influenced by what's called volunteerism
whereby it is the the will and the
ability to make decisions that
differentiates people from the rest of
the beasts and he said that the most
distinctive
characteristic of a human being is found
in our natural inherent will to
power
it's not simply an aspiration of
significance whereby every person has in
their heart a desire to have their life
count and be meaningful and you may be
driven for success or so and it's more
than that it is a will to dominate
it's that will that is manifested in the
pyramid structure of the corporate world
it is that will that is exhibited for
example in our own childhood games that
we play that are highly competitive and
intensely
designed for Domination I remember when
I was a kid one of the games that we
played on outside was called King of the
Hill we would find a dirt pile and one
guy would scramble up to the top of that
dirt pile and it was everybody else's
challenge to climb up the pile and push
him off the top of the pile and replace
him and of course the guy who was on the
top would do everything he could to
prevent being kicked off the top of the
mound and whoever was left standing at
the end of the game was declared to be
the King of the Hill and that's a child
childish
manifestation of the games that grown
people people play in trying to achieve
domination it's what triggers Wars and
economic competition and all of the rest
now Nietzsche does not see this as a bad
thing
he said that this is why we were what
we're all about is human beings and
what's bad is for the person out of his
own insecurity and out of his weakness
to fail to make the assault on the hill
because the decadence of modern man is
found in that he is a coward he lacks
the virtue of Courage but the Superman
is the man who is not afraid to exercise
his will to power to the ultimate level
indeed Nietzsche's greatest heroes from
history were those who became famous for
their conquests of others in the world
now over against
the will to power we see the negative
influence of religion which tries to
squelch this natural human spirit and
not only that the societal conventions
and Customs that militate against the
existential individual who walks to his
own drum beat
he says that that the 19th century
Europe is a culture and a society that
manifests what he called a herd morality
that people are slavish in their
following of societal customs and
conventions and are afraid to break out
of the pack and like stupid sheep they
just go around and follow whatever is
expected of them by their peers and that
also
squelches human Spirit and the
advancement of human greatness
now you may wonder why he would be on a
crusade for a Superman who would bring
us a new world order and a new Dawning
to humanity in light of his earlier
conviction
that there are no values there is no
meaning and there is no such thing
ultimately as right and wrong
if that's the case then even the
exercise of one's Will To Power would in
the final analysis be
an exercise in futility and an exercise
in meaninglessness and that's why and
Nichi agreed with that I mean he said
that's right it's contradictory but so
what it's nonsense it runs against
reason but never mind he said the chief
virtue or the chief characteristic of
the ubermans is courage but it is a
particular kind of Courage it's what
Nietzsche called dialectical
courage there's that term dialectical
again we saw it in Hegel we saw it in
Marx and now we see it in Nietzsche and
Nietzsche is talking about the dialectic
that operates in a real human
passionate tension
and the tension of dialectical courage
is this
that he says to people you've got to act
with courage
but if you act with courage
the results and the fruit of your
courageous act will be meaningless
but
do it anyway
because the only thing you have left is
to exercise your Will To Power and he
described his Superman in these
categories the existential hero is the
one Nietzsche said who sails his ships
into Uncharted seas and who builds his
house on the slopes of Vesuvius now what
is Vesuvius
Vesuvius of course is an active volcano
and for person to build their home on
the side of Mount Vesuvius is to have an
attitude of defiance towards the blind
impersonal forces of nature and against
what we might call fate
the man who takes his Destiny into his
own hand and According to Nietzsche is
subject to the values or the Customs or
the laws of no one else but he has the
courage
to create his own values to live by his
own rules and in a sense he becomes the
anti or anti-hero that is so often
celebrated in the modern film industry
or he's the Dennis Rodman of the
philosophical world who challenges all
of the uh
conventions and does all things that are
outrageous in the eyes of the public but
nevertheless continues to dominate as a
basketball player in one sense he would
be the embodiment or incarnation of the
nietzschean hero
now
Nature's views on these sort of things
as I said were in large measure
formulated while he was in his uh his
educational developmental stage
he wrote his doctoral thesis on the
culture of ancient Greece and he
compared and contrasted two images or
two heroes from the ancient Greek system
which he saw in radical tension and
conflict with each other the one was the
figure of Apollo
and Apollo represents the Golden Age of
Greek culture the Greek ideal the ideal
of perfect form
and Symmetry and coherency and
consistency such was seen in the
philosophy and the art and the music of
classical Greek that was the spirit of
Apollo which became the idealized spirit
of Western Civilization over against
Apollo in the ancient world was the
figure of dionysius and you've heard of
dionysius as the god of the grape you
know related to Bacchus and so on and
that there were religions devoted to the
worship of dionysius and what they did
was in order to achieve communion with
the deities they had to get past the
orderly control of the brain and the
mind and the conscience on the human
Spirit to be released from these
restraints that conscience brings to us
and so in the dionysian frenzy
the basic point of the frenzy was to
become so intoxicated with wine that you
could then be released to be engaged in
unbridled sexual orgies and so be so out
of control and stoned that in this state
of of ecstasy one would then have this
mystical communion with the God
dionysius and dionysius became the
anti-symbal of ancient Greece dionysius
became not the symbol of order and
purpose and Harmony but the symbol of
Chaos
and the symbol of willful Disobedience
to Convention
and and in his doctoral dissertation he
praised the image of dionysius rather
than the image of Apollo because he was
convinced of another ancient Greek idea
which was
the cyclical view of history and which
Nietzsche described as the myth of
Eternal recurrence the myth of Eternal
recurrence that the Christian view sees
history on a progressive linear path
that is moving always towards the
Fulfillment of the consummation of the
kingdom of God the other philosophies of
history of the 19th century will ever
were evolutionary in scope assuming an
optimistic
Omega point of fulfillment rather the
ancient myth
was of Eternal recurrence was that
history is cyclical it has no particular
beginning it is not moving towards some
particular purposive Destiny but is
simply going round and round forever in
an endless Circle beginning with nothing
and ending with nothing going absolutely
nowhere if you want to catch the spirit
of this you remember the movie They
Shoot Horses Don't They Jane Fonda
starred in that film red buttons was in
it some others and it was storing that
the filmed in the the period that was
suggested was The Depression period
where at that time where people were out
of work unemployed selling apples on the
street corner for a nickel that one of
the favorite pastimes in America was the
marathon dance it also gave people an
opportunity to to make some extra cash
and in this film these people were
engaged in this marathon and the man
who's the Master of Ceremonies in order
to facilitate the the the event and make
people drop out he would increase the
speed of the Promenade and make people
move around the room in a rapid Circle
and as he was doing that in a diabolical
way he would taunt them and tease them
and say round and round and round there
you go and where they stop nobody goes
nobody knows and then at the end and the
tragic consequences of the end Jane
Fonda gave the expression when they were
contemplating suicide because of the
utter meaninglessness of this whole
experience and the utter futility of it
she raised the question rhetorically
which was the film's title They Shoot
Horses Don't They
in other words if life is nothing but a
marathon that goes round and round and
is going nowhere and you're caught up in
the myth of Eternal recurrence then
really the only significant question as
later existentialists raised left to
observe was the question of suicide well
as I said in his later years
Nietzsche
spoke of horses as his brothers
and his sister
sold tickets
to The Lunatic Asylum where he was
kept because his brother was famous and
she was exploiting her brother's Fame
and dementia and exercised her own Will
To Power
and Nietzsche in his final days signed
his personal letters with the signature
the crucified one is in his madness he
saw himself
as The Reincarnation of Christ